# 借着这锅的热度
Use the heat from the wok
# 这种方法鸡排牛排 都可以炸
You can also fry chicken fillets or steaks with this method
# 猪通脊 很简单
Simply fillet this pork tenderloin
# 你看咱们斩几刀断断筋
Score the fillets to break down the connective tissues
# 另外一会儿腌的时候还入味
It also helps the marinade to penetrate into the meat later
# 省的它卷了是不是
And prevents the fillets from curling up
# 咱们找一个东西腌腌就行了
Let’s find a plate to marinate them
# 椒盐是粤菜的东西
Salt and pepper are common in Cantonese Cuisine
# 山东菜也有椒盐 但是味道不能一样
There are also salt and pepper dishes in Shandong Cuisine, but the flavours are different
# 这个看样子要复杂一点
This looks a bit complex
# 如果说咱们家里做就没那么复杂了
But we don’t have to make it so complex when cooking at home
# 搁点黄酒 搁点盐
Just marinate with some huangjiu rice wine, some salt
# 搁点葱姜 腌腌它就行
And some spring onions and ginger
# 先在弄点淮盐
Firstly, add some huaiyan salt
# 师父这淮盐是怎么做的
How to make huaiyan salt, master?
# 其实就是把盐炒热了加五香粉
It’s just toasted salt with some added five-spices
# 先入入底味儿
Use huaiyan salt to form the base flavour
# 然后这个是什么你知道吗
Do you know what this is?
# 沙姜粉
Sand ginger powder
# 什么东西别太多
Don’t add too much of anything
# 吉士粉 增香的
Add custard powder to increase the aroma
# 搁点玫瑰露 我说在这闻半天了就是香
Add some rose water. I have been sniffing this fragrance for a while
# 咱们在家没这么复杂 就搁点黄酒
Don’t make it this complex at home. Just use huangjiu rice wine
# 你闻闻这味 很香了 清香
Smell this. It’s so delightfully fragrant
# 它（粤菜）跟咱们（鲁菜）的
This marinating technique in Cantonese Cuisine
# 腌法就不一样
Is different from what’s in Shandong Cuisine
# 你看这么大 但是吃起来很嫩
This egg looks large, but tastes tender
# 这个鸡蛋清咱就不要了 只要蛋黄
We don’t use the egg white. We only need the yolk
# 他们浆肉好些都是用蛋清
A lot of people marinate the meat with egg whites
# 其实蛋黄它的优势应该是
In fact, the egg yolk has its advantage
# 比蛋清更脆 外表更脆了
It makes the meat crispier on the outside
# 这时候咱弄点粉子 玉米淀粉
Now add some cornstarch
# 接着抓
Keep massaging
# 其实师父这个东西如果在家里做
Master, if we make such dishes at home
# 真是一通百通了
We just need to master the one to master all
# 有的时候我在家里一不注意
Sometimes I’m not aware that
# 淀粉也没有了
I’m running out of starch at home
# 就直接使面粉也开始招呼
So I just use flour instead
# 其实没问题
It’s absolutely fine
# 美食它代表着一种生活态度
Gourmet food represents an attitude toward life
# 其实不一定太拘泥一个方式
You don’t have to limit yourself to one way
# 给我点水来
Give me some water
# 来点水 稍微抓点水
Marinate with a touch of water
# 因为这是干淀粉 它稠点
Because of the dry cornstarch, it’s a bit too thick
# 各种香味都出来了 复合的味道
All aromas have come out. It’s such a complex flavour
# 这就差不多了
Almost done
# 然后封点油 行了
Add a drizzle of oil. That’s enough
# 你看这个淀粉似有似没 这肉很润
The cornstarch is on spot, and the meat is incredibly moist
# 咱就开火了
Heat on
# 热锅凉油
Hot wok and cold oil
# 这个（猪排）煎也行
You can also pan-fry the fillets
# 这方法多种多样
It works with different kinds of cooking methods
# 美食没有那么深的定义
Gourmet food doesn’t have a profound definition
# 椒盐的小料 很简单
Simple ingredients to make the salt and pepper sauce
# 用这个小勺咱擓点椒盐 够吧
A spoon of huaiyan salt. Should be enough
# 这就不少了
That’s a decent amount
# MJ味特别大
Maggi seasoning is extra umami
# 网友朋友们 你看小料
These are the minor ingredients
# 干葱碎 青椒碎 红椒碎
Finely chopped onions, green peppers, red peppers
# 淮盐 MJ 黄酒 记住了
Huaiyan salt, Maggi seasoning, and huangjiu rice wine. Write it down
# 这会油差不多了
The oil should be ready by now
# 师父这大概几成热
How hot is the oil, master?
# 这大概得有个五六成热
It’s about 150 to 180 degrees centigrade
# 这个到最后的口感
When it’s finished, the texture of the fillets
# 是不是应该是外焦里嫩的
Should be crispy on the outside, and tender on the inside
# 外焦里嫩的肉一定要注意
Remember, to create such perfect texture
# 千万不能温油下锅
Never put meat in warm oil
# 把里边的水分都耗干了
It will dry the meat out
# 这粉子你要太薄了也不好
The cornstarch shouldn’t be too thin either
# 太薄了它就 那水分锁不住了 它不嫩
It wouldn’t be able to lock the juice if it's too thin. So the meat wouldn’t be as tender
# 这种方法鸡排牛排都可以炸
You can also fry chicken fillets or steaks with this method
# 再炸会 让它彻底炸透了
Fry for a few minutes more so the fillets are well cooked
# 然后再上点颜色
And beautifully coloured
# 这就差不多了 再复炸一下 脆一点
That’s about it. Double fry them later to make them crispier
# 油温坐高坐热
Wait for the oil temperature to rise
# 你看 这就酥了
Look, this is what I call crispy
# 复炸 复炸主要目的是表皮更脆
Now, double fry the fillets. The purpose of this is to make the crust even crispier
# 可以了 你看这颜色多漂亮
Done. Look how gorgeous this colour is
# 淡淡的金黄色 到你配合了
In beautiful light golden. Now do me a favour
# 把这汁一倒
Pour the sauce in
# 借着这锅的热度
Use the heat from the wok
# 你看这香 香气四溢 这是烹
Look at this. The fragrance is everywhere. This is called ‘peng’ (fry quickly in hot oil and stir in sauce)
# 满厨房都是香的
The fragrance is all over the kitchen
# 这汁一下就吸到肉排里去了
The fillets absorbed the sauce right away
# 一人来一块吧
One fillet each
# 先给我师姐 你先来你最小
Shijie first. You are the youngest, go for it
# 我下手了
I’ll just use my hand
# 师父那我也了下手
I’ll also eat with my hand, master
# 咸香 外焦里嫩
Savoury and fragrant. Crispy on the outside, and tender on the inside
# 复合味 太棒了
The complexity of flavours is just terrific
# shift forward 00:04:05,300
# 好多现在炒宫保鸡丁的
Nowadays, a lot of people who make kung pao chicken
# 都犯了一个致命的错误
Are making a critical mistake
# 谈到宫保鸡丁这道菜
When it comes to kung pao chicken
# 其实我有特殊的感情
I actually have a special relationship with it
# 七三年我中学毕业以后
After I graduated from middle school in 1973
# 没插队就进入学校
I enrolled into the culinary school directly
# 当时我记得我们老师张晨
I remember the kung pao chicken made by our teacher Zhang Chen
# 做这宫保鸡丁
At that time
# 太香了  太好吃了
Was incredibly fragrant and tasty
# 从这之后 这道菜给我
Since then, this dish
# 留下的是最深的印象
Has left me with the deepest impression
# 记忆犹新
It remains fresh in your memory
# 后来十六七岁
Later, when I was 16, 17 years old
# 因为什么
This happened
# 我跟你们两个师叔庹有华
I was familiar with you two’s shishu Tuo Youhua
# 庹师叔 我们很熟
Aka Shishu Tuo
# 师爷（庹代良）的儿子
The son of Shiye Tuo Dailiang
# 我们因为是同班同学
As we were classmates
# 一起在学习烹饪
We learnt cooking together
# 有幸的跟跟老爷子
And we were lucky enough to learn from Shiye
# 老上他们家 跟老爷子认识
We always went to their house and got to know Shiye
# 当时老爷子在我心中就一个神
At that time, in my eyes, Shiye was simply the God
# 前门饭店的总厨
He was the executive chef of Qianmen Hotel
# 为什么刚才说
Why did I just say
# 我对这个菜情有独钟
That I had a special fondness of this dish?
# 上你师爷他们家去
Because every year when I went to Shiye’s house
# 每年师父都亲自炒宫保鸡丁
He would always make kung pao chicken in person
# 说实话一年到时候就盼着去他们家
To be honest, I was just looking forward to going to their house for a whole year
# 看师父炒宫保鸡丁
To watch the master making kung pao chicken
# 所以说这份鸡丁
So, the kung pao chicken
# 今年我六十 带着我从十六岁开始
Has companied me since I was 16
# 走到今天 一直陪伴着
All the way till today when I’m 60
# 所以说今天
So now
# 我们重点说说这宫保鸡丁
Let’s talk about kung pao chicken in more details
# 宫保鸡丁这道菜
I learnt this dish
# 从这之后跟师父学
From the master
# 跟你庹师爷学过
Your Shiye Tuo
# 因为什么
Why
# 我跟庹师爷这个经历非常丰富
I had a long and wonderful relationship with Shiye Tuo
# 我跟他学的什么 学的是做人
What I learnt the most from him was how to be a better person
# 我今天跟你们徒弟说
I always tell you disciples and apprentices nowadays
# 其实我们说了半天菜
That although we are learning how to cook
# 关键是我们学做人
It’s crucial to learn how to become a better person
# 你做人做好了
If you are a good character
# 比如说大家都愿意帮你
Others would love to help you
# 愿意把东西掏心掏肺的给你
And give you their best willingly
# 你做人做不好 别人都躲着你
If you are a bad character, on the other hand, others would try to avoid you
# 所以说我今天可能多啰嗦两句
I might have said a few more words today
# 先把人做好
But you must first become a good person
# 这是根
This is the root
# 在家里边你师爷手把手的教我
Your Shiye taught me how to make kung pao chicken in the old days
# 这宫保鸡丁过去怎么做
Step by step in his house
# 因为他是按照老的传统的做法
Because he followed the traditional ways
# 实际上我跟你师爷学的同时
In fact, in the meantime I learnt from Shiye
# 因为庹有华的关系
Because of Shishu Tuo Youhua
# 当时你庹师叔在四川饭店当厨师长
Being an executive chef at Sichuan Hotel at that time
# 我又跟陈松如老爷子又有所接触
I was also in contact with Chef Chen Songru
# 两位在京城德高望重的川菜大师
These two highly reputable Sichuan Cuisine master chefs in Beijing
# 在我人生的厨艺道路上
Provided me with tremendous help
# 给了我不少的帮助
In my career as a chef
# 所以说我从他们身上学到了
So I learnt to cook the authentic traditional flavours
# 正宗的这种老的味道
From both of them
# 我记得八四年的时候
I remember, in 1984
# 整个旅游局
The National Tourism Administration
# 全旅游局系统了之后考试
Implemented systematic culinary tests for all succeeding chefs
# 那时候考试难 六个菜
The tests were quite hard as we had to cook 6 dishes
# 八四年我是整个旅游局的第一名
I was ranked number 1 in the National Tourism Administration among all chefs
# 然后宫保鸡丁 十分满分
And I scored 10 out of 10 on kung pao chicken
# 所有的评委 七个评委
All seven judges
# 全部给我的都是满分
Gave me 10
# 我在宴会在上这道菜经常出现
I cooked this dish all the time for banquets
# 华都饭店当年主要是宴会太多
Huadu Hotel held so many banquets those years
# 宴会 大量的宴会你都做不完
Endless banquets
# 这段经历磨练我在哪儿呢
What did I learn from that experience?
# 我就把这鸡丁给改了
I changed the diced chicken in the dish
# 因为鸡丁它上不了档次
Because diced chicken was not presentable enough to be served in banquets
# 就改成大盘 招呼
I served kung pao chicken in large plates
# 用什么啊 用鸡腿肉改成宫保鸡花
With chicken thighs cut into the flower shape
# 大宫保鸡花 那吃着过瘾啊
It was so satisfying to eat big pieces of flower shaped kung pao chicken
# 腌透了以后红亮红亮的 我的天呐
The chicken was bright red after thoroughly marinating. Oh my god
# 特别受欢迎
It was particularly popular
# 那个年代我就给改良了
I revised the dish during that time
# 改良之后这个鸡打鸡花
With this flower shaped chicken thighs
# 在腌制的时候
When marinating
# 过去那种酱油 盐 料酒腌
We used traditional soy sauce, salt, huangjiu rice wine
# 葱姜水 毛姜水
Spring onion and ginger water, and zingiber water
# 反正都是这些东西
It was always marinated with these ingredients
# 腌出来打完了很嫩
The chicken was super tender after marinating
# 没有现在这么多添加剂
We didn’t have so many food additives as today
# 主要是那时候用两种油
Essentially we used two kinds of oil
# 我用什么油封呢
Which oil did I use for confit?
# 用北京的花椒和四川的花椒
I fried Sichuan peppercorns from both Beijing and Sichuan
# 两种花椒炸出的油
In the oil to extract their flavours
# 用这个油 腌好了以后封这个菜
And then confit the marinated chicken with the infused oil
# 当你鸡滑了下去之后
When you fried the chicken later
# 味道倍儿足 味道已经很浓了
The flavour was already very intense and sophisticated
# 又有淡淡的那种花椒的香气味
With a light touch of the aroma from Sichuan peppercorns
# 所以说这个菜
So this dish
# 就这菜出来就与众不同
Immediately stood out once it was revealed
# 其实在改革当中 创新当中
Actually, during culinary reform and innovation
# 其实一个小的动作
A simple and small move
# 就能改变菜的整个的味道
Could change the entire flavour of a dish
# 你看我从二十几岁走到今天六十岁
Since I was in my twenties till today when I’m 60
# 这宫保鸡丁从来就特别火
Kung pao chicken has always been a crowds’ favourite
# 其实无非就两个味型
It has nothing but two versions
# 一个是过去的糊辣
One is the traditional ‘hula’ flavour (spicy with slightly burnt spices)
# 现在属于荔枝口
The other one is called ‘lizhikou’ (added equal amounts of sugar, vinegar, and starch slurry)
# 荔枝口比较大的 有点小糖醋了
Some of the stronger ‘lizhikou’ dishes could even be called sweet and sour chicken
# 过去就是什么糊辣
In the old days, kung pao chicken was predominantly ‘hula’
# 主要是以糊辣为主 糊辣咸鲜
This popular flavour was smoky, spicy, savoury and umami
# 它以这个为主
The majority of the dish were cooked that way
# 现在这东西 糖和醋的比例大了
But now, more sugar and vinegar are being used
# 过去的就是几种流派
In the past, we only had a few styles of cooking kung pao chicken
# 四川饭店的不让加辣椒面
At Sichuan Hotel, chilli powder was not allowed to be added to the dish
# 就是原汁原味
The flavour must be original and authentic
# 你师爷饭店包括北京饭店
While your Shiye, along with Beijing Hotel
# 可以加辣椒面
Added chilli powder to it
# 在煸炒当中 然后推辣椒面
During stir-frying, chilli powder would be generously incorporated
# 这辣椒面有一种非常
The chilli powder
# 辣椒这种清香的
Had an intense spicy aroma
# 那种味道也很好吃
And it was equally delicious
# 这两个东西都很好吃
Both styles tasted fantastic
# 都各有各的特色
And both had their own characteristics
# 峨嵋酒家为主的宫保鸡丁 糖醋
Sweet and sour kung pao chicken from restaurants led by Emei Hotel
# 现在又是一个流派的版本
Has now become another noticeable style
# 跟师父这么多年 总结了很多经验
After so many years following my master, I have summarised quite a few tips from my experience
# 我觉得比方说
For instance
# 从宫保鸡丁来说
Taking kung pao chicken for example
# 我觉得从两个点入手
In my opinion, we can start with two points
# 第一点 传承的东西口味的不要变
Firstly, don’t change the flavour of something that has been passed on for generations
# 宫保鸡丁也好
No matter it’s diced kung pao chicken
# 宫保鸡花也好
Or flower-shaped kung pao chicken
# 宫保鸡条也好
Or kung pao chicken fingers
# 改变一下 原来滑油
If you want some changes, chicken used to be fried
# 我现在等于是
Now I can do this
# 给它挂师父做的生熟糊
Coat the chicken with the shengshuhu batter made by master
# 挂完了以后
Once coated
# 我底下是铺一铺披萨
Lay a pizza underneath the chicken
# 我上头撒上奶酪 往上一烤
Then sprinkle some cheese on top, and roast the whole thing
# 这是我的想法
That’s just my thought
# 我也不知道这样对不对
I’m not sure if it would work
# 师父您给看看徒弟这种想法
Could master provide some feedback on this idea?
# 其实你还算有想法
You actually have some interesting ideas
# 我要纠正的问题是什么问题
What I must rectify here is that
# 好多现在炒宫保鸡丁的
Nowadays, a lot of people who make kung pao chicken
# 都犯了一个致命的错误
Are making a critical mistake
# 在传承当中其实忽视了什么
What they have overlooked in the culinary inheritance
# 忽视了小料
Is the use of minor ingredients
# 小魏 同样的葱 比如宫保鸡丁
Xiao Wei, for spring onions, when you follow my steps
# 你看着跟着我
To making kung pao chicken
# 我一个是在调汁的时候
I add in spring onions and ginger
# 把葱姜蒜搁在里边
When making the sauce
# 还有一个是煸炒的
As well as when stir-frying
# 这样的它两方面加起来
With both steps combined
# 能够刺激这个东西的香味
The aroma of the spring onions can be stimulated
# 全部给激发出来
And extracted
# 但是你看 现在好多炒宫保鸡丁
But now, a lot of people only use spring onion sticks
# 大部分全是葱骨碌
When cooking kung pao chicken
# 这个根本就不是传承
This is not proper inheritance
# 它里头香味熟不了
The aroma would be trapped
# 它释放不出来
Rather than being released
# 其实葱那香气是在里边
The aroma of the spring onions is actually inside the stems
# 它里边的出不出来
And it wouldn’t be able to come out
# 我给它切了
Unless I cut them into smaller pieces
# 切完了两大好处
There are two benefits of cutting the spring onions
# 第一个是香味激发出来了
The first one is that the aroma can be released
# 还有一个是什么
And the other one is that
# 我搁多少葱它都看不见葱
You wouldn’t see the spring onions no matter how many I put into the dish
# 它永远突出这主料
So the main ingredients can always stand out
# 这过去传承
Knowing how to use minor ingredients
# 隐藏的其实是最大的好处
Is actually the real hidden gem of the culinary inheritance
# 其实在这
From the past
# 你们要知道这个好处
You must understand it
# 在这基础上 刚才小魏讲的
Based on this, like what Xiao Wei just said
# 你再激发你的灵感去创新
You can then use your inspirations to innovate
# 其实最重要的那底味拿住
The most crucial thing is to hold onto the base flavours
# 一下拿足了它
Firmly
# 这个菜 任何菜都是这样
It applies to kung pao chicken and any other dishes